《斯巴达克斯：血与沙》
《揭露》
看到一个曾经高高在上的人 落魄至此
It wounds my heart, to see a man once so elevated,
真令人伤心
plummet to such depths.
你那个狗腿子Ashur
Your dog Ashur.
他向我摇尾乞怜的那一套
Was he always upon your leash,
都是你授命的吧?
even when licking my ass?
他忠贞不二
His loyalty never wavered.
此人骗人不偿命
The man is most skilled in deceit.
或者你只是一厢情愿
Or perhaps you were too blinded
不愿认清事实
by envy to perceive the truth.
你自欺欺人
You flatter yourself.
难道你就没垂涎过我的训练场?
Did you not have eyes towards my ludus?
我的战神?
My champions?
还有我老婆?
My wife?
你妄想掠夺Batiatus家族的荣耀
You would steal glory from the House of Batiatus.
可惜现在偷鸡不着蚀把米
Yet here you are with nothing but blood and
好凄凉呀
sand for your efforts.
卡普亚民众 迟早会认清你是什么人
Capua will see you for what you are.
将谋害行政官的凶手
The man who brought the Magistrate's murderer
绳之以法的民族英雄?
to justice, a hero of the people?
啊 愿天神保佑我 不要受池鱼之殃
Ah, may the gods protect me from their wrath.
Crixus三两下就能干掉对手
Crixus makes quick work of his opponent.
我得回上席...
I must return to the pulvinus...
去宣布你的处决令
to announce your execution.
戏演得真好 Batiatus
Well played, Batiatus.
我低估你了
I underestimated you.
你不是第一个栽跟头的人
You're not the first to die for that mistake.
为你而战!
For you!
Crixus为追念您丈夫 争得了荣誉
Crixus honors the memory of your husband.
我们也一样
As do we all.
我们应当抛却伤心的过往...
We should put these dark times behind us...
以Solonius之血...
and with Solonius' blood...
来祭奠我们的伤痛
amend our grief.
Crixus! Crixus 万岁!
Crixus! Crixus!
Crixus! Crixus! Crixus 万岁!
Crixus! Crixus! Crixus!
我要求跟Batiatus说话
I request words with Batiatus,
结果你却一个人回来
yet you return absent the man.
他有其它事在忙
Other matters occupy his attention.
我让民众整整一周难以忘怀
I've pressed for audience all week.
主人却忘了他的战神是谁
Dominus forgets who his champion is.
是你忘了身份才对
It is you who forgets title,
忘了主人和奴隶的身份
master and slave.
抱歉
Apologies.
成为战神后 我屡屡犯错
I have made many mistakes since becoming Champion.
我马上去反省 改正错误
Know that I intend to rectify them shortly.
卡普亚的市民们!
Good Citizens of Capua!
我站在你们面前
I stand before you,
伤痛欲绝
the sting of tears yet hot upon my cheek,
要惩治一个罪大恶极的
to redress a most vile crime
人民公敌
against our city and our hearts.
他就是谋杀Titus Calavius行政官的凶手!
The murder of Magistrate Titus Calavius!
此人利欲熏心
His life stolen
不惜痛下杀手
for lust of profit and advancement.
让慈祥睿智的行政官
His warmth and guidance
和我们...
torn from our hands...
还有他亲爱的妻儿 天人永隔!
and those of loving wife and noble son!
今天让我们见证正义的裁决!
Yet today we shall witness justice!
伤我们至深的卑劣罪人
The base criminal that has so wounded us
将在角斗场受到处决!
shall be executed at gladium!
Solonius入场!
Enter Solonius!
人民公敌!
Enemy of the people!
无耻之徒!
Fucking pig!
背信弃义的小人!
Traitor!
扯烂他的舌头!
Slice his traitor tongue off!
死马屁精!
You fucking pig!
该由谁来执行处决呢?
And who shall balance the scales?
谁又能让我们的城市重归光荣呢?
Who shall restore honor to our city?
斯巴达克斯! 斯巴达克斯! 斯巴达克斯!
Spartacus! Spartacus! Spartacus!
只有他!
There is but one man!
死亡之影的屠灭者!
The Slayer of Theokoles!
送雨的使者!
The Bringer of Rain!
斯巴达克斯...
Spartacus...
卡普亚战神!
Champion of Capua!
你在处决中逃过一死 色雷斯人
You survived your execution, Thracian.
当时正是在这片沙场
Upon these very sands.
或许Solonius也能将历史重演
Perhaps good Solonius will fare as well.
我倒觉得希望渺茫
I would not expect it.
开始!
Begin!
该死的 来打我啊!
Fight me, damn it!
为什么斯巴达克斯不还手?
Why does Spartacus not strike in return?
他这么做 有助于刺激民众怒焰滔天
He but extends the moment, to the favor of the crowd.
这个恶棍马上就会伏法了
The villain's blood will flow soon enough.
你丈夫真像天神赐下的礼物
Your husband has been a gift from the gods.
没有他的帮忙 Numerius肯定茫然无措
Numerius would be lost without his support.
这场角斗赛 能让他得到莫大的安慰
He gains great comfort in the act.
我们都深感安慰
The comfort is ours.
有朝一日 他也会成为一位好父亲
He will make a fine father, when the day comes.
瞧 斯巴达克斯砍到他了
Look, Spartacus draws blood.
你有角斗功底
You are not absent skill.
也有生存的欲望
Nor desire to live.
瞧见了?
You see?
Solonius玩儿完了
Solonius comes to his end.
这不是众望所归么?
And who would not wish it?
你丈夫的去世 令罗马的街上 泪流成河
The streets of Rome are wet with tears of your loss.
Ilithyia 你还没有答复我们
We have not received word from you, Ilithyia.
你和你丈夫说过了吗?
Did you speak to your husband?
关于资助Batiatus家族的事?
About patronage for the House of Batiatus?
说得很详细
At length.
他明天会来卡普亚
He comes to Capua a day hence,
亲自商讨此事
to discuss the matter personally.
民众的呼声
The roar of the crowd.
再没有比这更荣耀的了
There is no sound more glorious.
这是你能听到的 最后的呼声了
The last you shall hear.
你跟错了人
You take the wrong life.
你的主人Batiatus 是个恶棍
Your master Batiatus, is the villain.
不久 他就会跟你一样
And shall join you presently.
杀了他! 杀了他! 杀了他!
Kill! Kill! Kill!
斯巴达克斯! 斯巴达克斯! 斯巴达克斯!
Spartacus! Spartacus! Spartacus!
我不会让Agron为了兄弟情义
I would not have Agron risk himself
去冒险
on behalf of brotherly bond.
将来 让他和Duro分开角斗
See him separated from Duro in future games.
那么 斯巴达克斯呢?
And, what of Spartacus?
没人召见 让他焦躁不安
He grows restless at not receiving audience.
审判Solonius让我焦头烂额
The proceedings with Solonius have filled my attentions.
让Mira去抚慰他
Send Mira to occupy his thoughts.
明早我再传召他
I will summon him in the morning.
遵命 主人
Dominus.
长袍 尊显出智者的高贵!
Robes, fit for a man of breeding and intelligence!
很衬你呢
You wear them well.
今天看到Solonius引颈被戮
Today beheld the end of Solonius.
场面之壮观
A welcomed spectacle, given purchase
全拜你的忠诚和狡黠所赐
by your loyalty and cunning.
你应该立即离开训练场
You shall be removed from the ludus immediately.
离开?
Removed?
住到庄园去吧
You'll reside in the villa.
地位高升 远离贱民
Elevated far above the common men,
让自己的狡黠才智 更有用武之地
your devious fucking mind close to elbow.
我感激得说不出话了
Gratitude seizes the tongue.
哈 或许来个小妞 可以帮你重现辩才
Well perhaps a woman will aid in the untangling of it.
我手下的女奴
Name any slave, and the wet joys
随便你挑
of her body are yours.
我承认 我的确有所需求
I confess to certain longings.
我想要个没被别人玩过的小妞
For one not yet soiled by the other men.
告诉我名字 我帮你达成心愿
Give name to your desire, and see it fulfilled.
抱歉打扰
Apologies.
主人叫我来的
My presence was commanded.
Batiatus么?
By Batiatus?
是他派我来的
His words set me to purpose.
但我很高兴...
But they were gladly received...
我照顾受伤的你
I tend your wound.
当你犯下命案的时候
Stand guard at your request while you
我遵照你的要求 帮你放哨
stain hands with blood.
可你连碰都不让我碰?
And you discard a simple touch?
我在想事呢
My mind is taken with other thoughts.
那不妨告诉我是什么事
Then break open head and share them.
恐怕Batiatus在怀疑 我和Aulus的死有关
I fear Batiatus suspects my hand in Aulus' death.
他似乎没这意思
He appears absent the weight of pressing concern.
那他为何不召见我?
Then why does he not grant me audience?
Aulus断气前 到底说了什么
What secrets did Aulus reveal in dying breath,
让你如此愤怒?
that so inflamed?
他杀了Sura
That his hand robbed Sura of life.
而且是奉Batiatus之命
By command of Batiatus.
你想复仇!
You plan vengeance!
千万不要这样做!
You cannot do this!
- 斯巴达克斯...  - 她不是这么叫我的!
- Spartacus...  - That is not what she called me!
我再也听不到她呢喃我的真名了
Never again will I hear her whisper my true name.
再也感受不到 爱人呢喃的欢乐
Or taste the joy of it on her lips.
我要看着他一败涂地
I will see the light fade from his eyes,
为我妻子偿命
or join her in the attempt.
哪怕赔上我的命?
At expense of my life?
你这个色雷斯人 根本不懂罗马律法!
The Thracian does not know Roman law!
如果有一个奴隶杀了主人...
If one slave spills the blood of his master...
所有的奴隶都得陪葬
all are put to death.
人人都有自己的宿命
Each to his own fate.
我也一样
And I to mine.
你真是狂野...
You move with strong purpose...
全拜你的胜利所赐
Spurred, by your victory.
当我打败Pericles的时候
When I defeated Pericles,
你不在上席...
and you were not in the pulvinus...
没有你的注视
There is no meaning to glory,
荣耀毫无意义
without your eyes to witness.
我以后会一直注视着你
They will never again be absent.
Naevia啊?
Naevia?
快!
Hurry!
Quickly!
Naevia啊!
Naevia!
主人
Domina.
你在忙些什么 叫了半天也没人影?
What business do you attend, that you do not answer?
主人 我在拿酒
Fetching wine, Domina.
抱歉 我没听到...
Apologies, I did not hear...
别管酒了
Leave it.
主人要你办件事
There is a service required of you by Dominus.
看到你 真让我心跳不已
My heart quickens at such a vision.
拜托...
Please...
你大可放心
Set mind to ease.
我会既往不咎的
I cling to no grudge for past transgressions.
我不明白
I do not understand.
听说Barca获得自由后
You spoke with Doctore,
你和Doctore谈过
after it was said Barca secured his freedom.
我什么也没对他说
I told him nothing.
这无关紧要
A thing of no consequence.
仔细回想
Turn it from your thoughts,
就如此刻 我这般回想...
as I have turned it from mine...
为了获取...
in favor of more...
你的垂青...
intimate concerns...
多年来 我一直倾慕你的容颜
I have admired your beauty for many years.
你可知晓我的心意?
Were you aware of my affections?
我察觉 近来你的目光总落在我身上
I have felt your gaze linger of late.
无奈 我只能以目传情...
A gaze is all I could dare...
你所处的位置 超出我能力之外
your position placing you forever beyond my grasp.
纤细 成熟的Naevia啊
Delicate, ripe Naevia.
一直都是我的禁果
Always the forbidden fruit.
直至此刻...
Until now...
你在颤抖
You tremble.
从未有男人这样吻过你...
Has a man never kissed you...
轻抚你臀间撩人曲线...
caressed the soft curves of your hips...
进入你的胴体...
slipped inside of you...
主人知道我仍保有处女之身
Domina has seen me remain untouched.
所以我俩...
Then we are both...
都欠她人情
in her debt.
你像对待贱女一样 把她的身子送了出去!
You give her away as if a common whore!
自她孩童时起 我就一直保留她的贞操
I've preserved her chastity since she was a child,
只等将其作为礼物送予他人!
towards presenting it as gift!
贞操的唯一珍贵之处 就在于破处
The only gift of chastity is in its removal.
但要有一个配得起的男人!
By a man of worth!
而不是混账Ashur!
Not fucking Ashur!
Naevia一直是我最为信任的奴隶
Naevia has been my most trusted slave.
那混账叙利亚人
The thought of that fucking Syrian
心生邪念 行之不轨...
shoving his devious cock inside her...
这是对你的背叛 Quintus
It's a betrayal, Quintus.
这事必不可免
It is a necessity.
先将此中细节搁置一边 考虑一下
Set details of it aside, and shift mind
如何迎接Glaber吧
to Glaber's arrival.
他的赞助费 能使我们
His patronage brings to climax
达到鼎盛
all our labors.
当红日自Batiatus家族升起...
When the sun rises on the House of Batiatus...
一切都将改变
everything will change.
你那木头人 真跟Solonius一样遭罪
Your wooden man gives almost as much fight as Solonius.
每胜利一次
With each victory,
离我与你再战竞技场
I draw closer to facing you again in the arena.
夺回被你窃取的荣耀 就更近一步
And reclaiming stolen glories.
没有荣耀
There is no glory.
唯有鲜血
Only blood.
只为取悦那些罗马人 而血溅沙场
Spilled for the pleasure of the Romans.
看到我让你血溅沙场
And how they shall roar,
他们该怎样尖叫欢呼呢
when I spill your blood upon the sands.
斯巴达克斯!
Spartacus!
主人传召你
You are summoned.
你怕你永远没这机会了
I fear you will never have the chance.
瞅瞅你们都他妈在干什么!
Watch what you're fucking doing!
操
Fuck.
给我小心点!
Be careful with that!
是 主人
Dominus.
花在哪儿?
Where are the flowers?
去找个新女仆 再弄些花来!
Go find the new girl and bring the fucking flowers!
满屋子奴隶 每件事还他娘的要我亲自过问
A house full of slaves, have to do fucking everything myself.
啊! 卡普亚战神
Ah! The Champion of Capua graces us
驾临于此!
with his presence!
抱歉没能尽早迎接
Apologies for not receiving you sooner.
近来事端不断 我被折腾得心力憔悴
I have been consumed with the tumult of recent events.
变化真大啊
Much has changed.
脚下的世界瞬息万变
The world reforms at our feet,
每一寸土地都迫使我们
the very earth thrusting us
登向难以设想的高度!
to unimaginable heights!
花费不菲吧
At great cost.
不值一提!
Easily paid!
现下 Glaber副将正赶往这里
At this very moment Legatus Glaber
打算施予赞助费呢
thunders towards us to bestow patronage.
我知道你对此人心存芥蒂
I know your feelings towards the man.
我倒希望你暂且压制
I would ask that they be put aside,
为了更大的利益嘛
in favor of more noble pursuits.
Glaber从我怀中夺走Sura
Glaber took Sura from my arms.
可他并非取其性命之人
But he is not the man that took her life.
是Aurelia?
Aurelia?
您还有吩咐吗?
Would that be all?
没了 退下吧
Yep, fine, leave.
她在这儿做什么?
What is she doing here?
被我雇佣为奴 抵偿Varro欠下的债啊
Working beneath my employ, to pay off Varro's debts.
我会以我的胜金抵下债务
I pledged my winnings to such a cause.
- 你没告诉她吗?  - 当然说过
- You did not tell her this?  - Of course.
但她不要你的钱
She would have no coin from your purse,
也不要我的 除非是她自己
nor mine, unless it was obtained
劳动所得
by means of fair labor.
她愿意在Batiatus家族为仆
She wishes to serve the House of Batiatus,
直至债务偿清
until all his debts are balanced.
她是个好女人
She is a good woman.
值得敬重
And worthy of consideration.
她的确值得敬重
And she shall receive it in abundance.
现在告诉我 你这么急着
Now tell me, what matter were you so eager
找我干嘛?
to discuss with me?
我只想核实对Varro妻子的承诺
I merely sought word towards Varro's wife,
现在知道她的决定了
and that she had been provided for.
很好!
Excellent!
我们谈拢了啊
So all is well between us.
我要和斯巴达克斯单独说话
I require words with Spartacus.
我他妈凭什么答应你?
Why the fuck would I allow that?
因为我始终为你遗失门钥一事
Because my tongue remains silent
保守秘密
towards the gate key you lost.
你也不想我说出来吧?
You would have it remain so?
快点啊
Be quick.
机会就摆在你眼前 可你却放过了Batiatus
Opportunity presents itself, yet Batiatus lives.
暂时而已
For the moment.
昨晚 这房子里其他奴隶的命
Last night the lives of every slave
你还根本不在乎
under this roof meant nothing to you.
接着Aurelia出现了 然后你居然就有了良心!
Then Aurelia appears, and you grow a conscience!
Varro是我的兄弟
Varro was as a brother.
我不会让他的妻子受到伤害
I will not see his wife put at risk.
当你杀死了她丈夫的时候 她就已经受到伤害了
You put the woman at risk when you killed her husband.
Crixus啊!
Crixus!
一份告别礼物
A parting gift.
这是什么鬼东西?
What is this shit?
你跟Theokoles战斗的纪念品
A memento of your battle with Theokoles.
自从斯巴达克斯带来雨水之后
The city was filled with such novelties
这城市到处都是这种小饰品
after Spartacus brought the rains.
当然 制作工艺很粗糙
The craftsmanship was rather poor.
主人终于决定把你从角斗士中
Dominus finally decides to remove you
调出来了?
from the company of men?
调得可远了
Far removed.
主人在庄园里 给我安排了岗位
I have been given favored quarters within the villa.
我现在已经成了他的得力助手啦
To serve as our master's right hand.
也是他擦屁股的手
The one he wipes his ass with.
哈 用词用得多妙啊
Ah, a witty turn of phrase.
我会想念作为
One of many splendors I shall miss
角斗士的荣耀的
of being a gladiator.
你可从没当过角斗士
You were never a gladiator.
没有
No.
全拜你刺我大腿那一刀所赐
Not after your blade found itself in my leg.
就当我送你的礼物
My gift to you.
送完之后 确实让我得益不少啊
One that has given great reward.
我的地位
Everything I am,
我所拥有的一切 都是拜你所赐啊
everything I now possess, I owe to you.
不 把它放在阳台上
No, that goes to the balcony.
赶紧 副将就要到了
Quickly, the Legatus arrives.
新人做事 真叫人不满意
The new girl is slow to the task.
厚道点儿
An act of charity.
帮她找一个适合的岗位吧
We shall yet find proper use for her.
大日子啊 主人
A great day, Dominus.
这一天将永被铭记
One that shall be remembered.
副将人呢?
Where is the Legatus?
抱歉 我丈夫有事耽搁了
Apologies. My husband is delayed.
但是你答应过了
But you made promise.
放心 我会遵守的
Which will be well kept.
他还是会来拜访的
He yet intends proper visit,
但得请Batiatus
but requests good Batiatus give greeting
去城门迎接
upon entering the city.
荣幸之至!
A great honor!
他什么时候到?
When does he arrive?
马上就到
Now.
那我们得赶紧了!
We must hurry!
来
Come.
让我们到阳台去享用美食
Let us retire to the balcony to feast.
然后好好检讨一下你的时间观念
And review your sense of timing.
那样最好
I would love nothing more,
但是我必须赶回庄园
but I must return to the villa
去收拾一下东西
to gather my belongings.
收拾来干嘛?
To what end?
我要搬回罗马了!
I'm moving back to Rome!
但是你在卡普亚还没住多久啊
But your stay in Capua has been so brief.
没办法
Painfully.
但是我丈夫还要为执政官打仗啊
Yet now that my husband campaigns for praetor,
他坚持让我陪在他身边
he insists I remain at his side.
你没事吧?
Are you well?
脸色好苍白啊
The blood drains from your cheeks.
一想到你要走...
My heart but flutters at the...
我心里就堵得慌
the thought of losing you.
我们俩在一起的美好记忆
Memories of our time together will
想忘都难啊
fade only with difficulty.
Lucretia 你的友谊
Your friendship, Lucretia,
已经彻底改变了我的生活
has forever altered my life.
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
我有一个请求
I would make request.
找别人吧 我帮不了你
Ask another, if you seek it granted.
不是为我 而是为了我兄弟
It is not for me, but for my brother.
Batiatus下令我们分开角斗
Batiatus orders us parted.
Duro听到这消息 开心死了
Duro greets the news with laugh and fucking smile.
可我担心他独自一人 无法在竞技场活下来
Yet I fear he shall not survive the arena on his own.
我也是这么想的
You are not alone in the thought.
Batiatus非常看重你
Batiatus shows you much favor.
只要你帮我们说个情 他就能收回成命
A word from your lips could see the decision undone.
Batiatus除了自己 谁也不看重
Batiatus favors no one but himself.
看! 是副将啊!
Yeah! The Legatus!
Glaber副将!
Legatus Glaber!
您的到来 真是令卡普亚城荣光无限啊!
Your arrival honors the fair city of Capua!
我以为你会到城门口来迎接我
An honor I expected matched by greeting at the gate.
真是不好意思 我还以为是...
Well apologies. I had thought that..
这事姑且不论
Let us move past it.
自从我上次走后
My ears burn with reports of lawlessness
这里越来越目无法纪
since last I visited.
行政官的死实属不幸...
The Magistrate's murder was unfortunate...
这对于Ovidius和他的家族 更是如此
As was that of Ovidius and his family.
而现在 Crassus议员的表亲
And now the cousin of Senator Crassus
又失踪了
goes missing.
我们去我庄园吧 到那里再就这些事
Let us retire to my villa, and we can discuss these
好好详谈一下
and other matters at length.
我还是跟相关负责人谈吧
I prefer to speak with someone in authority.
Mercato还等着呢
Good Mercato awaits.
需要我陪您去吗?
I shall accompany you?
不必
That won't be necessary.
在你的庄园候着吧
Await me at your villa.
您何时回来呢?
When shall I expect you?
到时自有分晓
When I arrive.
Crixus! 主人传召你
Crixus! You are summoned.
我期待夜晚
I long for the night, to continue
能继续上次中断了的事
what was last interrupted.
我不能见你
I can not meet you.
就一晚而已
This but one night.
没必要这么小心
There's no cause for this.
当然有必要
Yes, cause.
足以使我们抱头痛哭
Enough to drown us both in tears.
主人把我送给了另一个人
Dominus has given me to another.
谁? 把名字告诉我!
Who? Tell me his name!
告诉你又能怎样?
What does it matter?
我们都活在梦中
We have lived in a dream.
现在我们都该醒醒了
And now we must awaken.
别感到烦恼了 强壮的Crixus啊
Do not be troubled, mighty Crixus.
卡普亚再次欢呼了你的名字
Capua cheers your name once more.
很快你就能从那该死的色雷斯人手中
Soon you will seize the mantle of Champion
夺回战神的荣耀
from that fucking Thracian.
然后一切都会回到
And everything shall be as it was
与Theokoles对战之前
before you fell to Theokoles.
我渴望那能够实现
I long for it to be so.
我也是啊
As do I.
有点不对劲啊...
Something's wrong...
主人 恕罪
Apologies, Domina.
Naevia啊!
Naevia!
那笨蛋把我招进城里
The shit fuck beckons me to the city,
就是为了把我像婊子一样一脚踢开!
only to spurn me like a thin wasted whore!
众神又他妈的
Once again the gods spread the cheeks
狠狠玩了我一次!
to ram cock in fucking ass!
也许该礼貌地提醒一下副将
Perhaps a gentle nudge, to remind the Legatus
你的重要性... ?
of your importance... ?
嗯 安排一下会面
Hmm, make the arrangements.
Glaber会对我俯首帖耳的
Glaber will bend to my fucking will.
不然就把他弄得很惨
Or break in the denying of it.
Lucretia啊!
Lucretia!
你得跟Ilithyia说一下...
You need to have fucking words with Ilithyia...
发生了什么事?
What's happened?
我怀上孩子了
I am with child.
你要当爸爸了 Quintus
You're to be a father, Quintus.
好啊 上酒!
Well, wine!
为这该死的房子干杯 啊!
Wine for the fucking house, eh!
我们得庆祝庆祝!
We must celebrate!
我们得庆祝庆祝
We must celebrate.
这该死的村子
This fucking village.
终于
Finally.
我还怕你晚上还要忙活呢
I had feared you absorbed for the night.
Mercato失职招惹的烂事
The curse of Mercato's incompetence.
Crassus表亲失踪了
Cousin of Crassus vanishes,
他那笨蛋脑袋里却还是毫无头绪
and no theory rattles around in his empty head.
不能用常理来推测啊
Theories pale against the obvious.
有人怀疑 Licinia的嘴巴
Licinia's tongue was suspected of lounging
在比他丈夫阳具更猥琐的地方
in less esteemed places than
打发时间...
around her husband's cock...
而我的嘴巴却要被迫用来进行
Whereas mine has made do with naught
无聊至极的社交谈话
but idle conversation.
我恐怕 那可没有你说的
I fear it may not have been as idle
那么无聊吧
as you would have me believe.
你跟Batiatus和他人老珠黄的婊子
What promises have you made Batiatus
做了什么交易啊?
and his faded bitch?
那人贩子用他水汪汪的眼睛望着我
The flesh monger looks to me with rheumy eyes,
充满了期望的样子
brimming with expectation.
我什么交易也没做 别瞎想了
I promise nothing, save word on their behalf
还是让我好好伺候我的老公吧...
to my dearly missed husband...
Batiatus就比他那些
Batiatus is little better
野兽蛮人的手下 强那么一点
than the beasts that bear his mark.
确实 但他们也提供了很多的乐趣啊
True, but they do provide a certain amusement.
顺应他们的要求吧
Humor their intent.
以你的身份 他们不敢要太多的
No more can be asked from a man of your station.
我已经履行了承诺 是时候回罗马了
My promise discharged, and we shall return to Rome.
更多文明世界的同伴
And more civilized company.
再取一个来
Fetch another.
别再给我打碎了
And hold onto it this time.
Aurelia啊
Aurelia.
能说句话么
I beg a moment.
单独说
Alone.
你不能生活在Batiatus的屋檐之下
You can not be under the care of Batiatus.
契约书已经签了
The deed is done.
那我就得让它无效
Then I shall see it undone.
我在竞技场的胜利...
My winnings in the arena...
根本就不是我要的
Are not fucking wanted.
Varro要我好好照顾你
Varro asked that I see you taken care of.
那就把他还给我啊
Then return him to me.
Varro的儿子
Varro's son.
他安全吗?
He is safe?
他和我哥哥待在一起
He stays with my brother.
这样就不用让他承受父亲的债务了
To be raised free of his father's debt.
但是他母亲不在身旁
Absent his mother.
你怀的孩子怎样了?
What of the child in carry?
它不是Varro的孩子
It was not fathered by Varro.
没有他 我...
Without him I...
我已经不去想了
I had it removed from my concerns.
也不会再去想你所做的了
As I would be from yours.
千万别相信Batiatus
Batiatus is not to be trusted.
别对他有任何的信赖
Do not lay faith in him.
我的丈夫死了
My husband is dead.
我的信赖也就跟着死了
And with him all faith.
如您所见 装修庄园
As your eyes witness, no coin has been spared
我可毫不吝啬啊!
in restoring the villa!
所有人进来 都会感到震惊
All will marvel upon privileged entry,
在有名的Batiatus家族历史前
and be humbled by the storied history
感到卑微!
of the house of Batiatus!
改变真是不小啊
It is a vast improvement.
嗯 众神真是眷顾他们啊
Hm, the gods have truly blessed them.
以后也会一直眷顾的
And continue to do so.
你如此地受到眷顾 为什么还要
If fortune so favors, why do you continue
这么肆无忌惮地 寻求我的帮助?
to press so brazenly for my support?
再大的眷顾也大不过
True fortune extends no further than
一个男人的野心
a man's ambitions.
而我的野心 远大于这竞技场的黄沙
Mine stretch well beyond the sands of the arena.
那是多大呢?
How far beyond?
直通行政部的门前
To the very doors of political office.
首先 还是要走出一小步
In a minor capacity. At first.
好吧 我们晚点再谈
Well, let us entertain it for a moment.
是何种地位的人给了你这般自信?
What men of status lend you their confidence?
在懦夫Solonius杀害行政官Calavius之前
Magistrate Calavius had voiced his endorsement.
行政官就已经声明了对我的认可
Before the coward Solonius forever stilled his tongue.
卑劣恶徒
Base villain.
他露出尖齿那副死相
The way he would stare with his teeth.
听闻这件悲剧 我深为所动
My heart is moved by the tragedy.
好在项上人头尚在
Yet my head remains fixed.
我与一个角斗士主结盟
What advantage would I gain by association
能得到什么好处?
with a lanista?
我的角斗士令民众群情激荡
My gladiators ignite the passion of the crowd,
使我得以达成我愿 他们雷鸣般的欢呼
lend name to my cause, and see their deafening cheers
也是Claudius Glaber你所需之物
transformed into demands for Claudius Glaber,
可以帮你早日获取执政官之位
and his desired position of Praetor.
他们非常喜欢Batiatus的手下
They do favor Batiatus' men like no others.
尤其是斯巴达克斯
Especially Spartacus.
那个色雷斯人
The Thracian.
我手下最低劣的士兵 却成为你最骁勇的角斗士
And what does it say that your finest gladiator
这又该怎么说?
was my worst soldier?
我是共和国最伟大的 角斗士主人
That I am the greatest lanista in the Republic.
我捕获蛮兽
For I have taken a wild beast,
并将他们锻造成神
and forged him into a god.
真是大言不惭啊
Its a bold claim.
我可是言出有据啊
Built on a foundation of fucking granite.
我倒想看看你是怎样做到的
I would see your words made flesh.
轻而易举啊
Easily conjured.
斯巴达克斯同其余人一样在场上训练
Spartacus trains in the square with the other men.
我曾经到过你这角斗场
I have descended into the bowels
当时可没注意到有这么个烂货
of your Ludus once before, and did not care for the stench.
传召那色雷斯人和你其他手下
Summon the Thracian to the villa,
一起到庄园来
along with the rest of your men.
所有人?
All of them?
所有人
All of them.
卡普亚战神
The Champion of Capua.
一个低等劣奴被冠之以如此头衔
A sad day when an honored city elevates a cur
真使这座荣耀之城蒙羞啊
to such position.
我看你已经教过那个劣奴不可多嘴了
I see you've taught the animal not to speak out of turn.
我想再看看这色雷斯人
And I would have demonstration of other tricks
学到的其他诀窍
the Thracian has learned.
给他解开锁链
Unchain him.
你想派我哪个手下去与他对抗?
Which of my men would you have oppose him?
谁也不派
None.
出列
Formation.
斯巴达克斯手持训练剑
Spartacus wields practice swords.
恐怕对他不利啊
I fear he's at a disadvantage.
我只是给他机会 让他证实传奇
I but give him chance to prove his legend.
Iovis出列
Iovis.
真令人兴奋
How exciting.
开战!
Begin!
Vesper! 还有Linus!
Vesper! Linus!
副将...
Legatus...
是你打开的这扇门 角斗士主人
You opened this door, lanista.
我们正要从此通过呢
And we shall pass through it.
看呐
Behold.
传奇已被证实
The legend is proved.
主人
Dominus.
这个野蛮人 曾令罗马蒙羞!!
This savage caused Rome great offense!
看来 你已经驯服他了
Yet it would appear that you have broken the man.
瞧他低眉顺眼的样儿
The way he bows his head in deference.
我倒想知道 如果我资助你的话
Would I be afforded such courtesies, I wonder,
他是否也会对我如此顺从?
if patronage were awarded?
他以及我的手下 都将唯你是从
He would be yours to command, as would all my men.
跪下
Kneel.
正当如此
And it shall be so.
副将大人
Legatus.
Crixus啊!
Crixus!
你个混账!
You fucking cunt!
冷静点!
Calm yourself!
奴隶们都疯了吗!
Slaves running wild!
这就是你赖以成名的人?
This is what you would have me give name towards?
你怎敢肆意妄为? 说啊!
What seizes your fucking wits? Speak!
我只是在品尝我的礼物 Crixus就发疯了
I yet but touch my gift, and Crixus goes mad.
我们同床共枕时 她的贞操早已荡然无存
I felt her maidenhood long absent when we lay together.
现在我知道是谁第一个上的她了
Now I know whose cock was in her first.
你个贱货!
You whore!
多久了?
How long?
他妈的多久了?
How fucking long?
你一直以来表面服帖
How long have you hidden laughter
背地里却在暗自窃喜!
behind a polite smile!
你勾引他
How long have you been luring him
让他上你这贱女 多久了?
to your filthy slave cunt?
这是什么? 这是什么?
What is it? What is it?
给我 拿来给我!
Give it to me. Give it to me!
从哪儿得来的?
How did you come by it?
我偷拿的
I took it.
打开门 你好和Crixus私通是吧
To open the gate. So you could lie with Crixus.
只有你一人知道我对他的感情
You alone knew of my feelings for him.
你却依然背叛我
And yet you betray me.
Crixus从未爱过你
Crixus never loved you.
他只是奉命行事
He did only as commanded.
Mira啊!
Mira!
主人
Domina.
给我拿把刀
Bring me a knife.
我们肯定会严惩Crixus
You have assurance Crixus will be punished.
我怕你会有所偏袒
I fear your hands too soft for the task.
你错了 他们如铁一般
You are mistaken. They are as steel,
麻木不堪
hardened to their purpose.
我也一样啊
As I to mine.
我们要回罗马
We return to Rome, absent
远离这纷争烦扰
unworthy entanglements.
你不能离开!
Do not turn from me!
你忘了你啥身份 角斗士主人!
You forget your place, lanista!
不 我没忘
No. I secure it.
把屋子给我打扫干净!
Clear the fucking room!
告诉Ashur 让他把礼物给副将送去!
Tell Ashur to bring our gift for the Legatus!
礼物就免了
Forget your gifts.
我会把这当做一场噩梦
I would part as from a troubling dream,
从此抛诸脑后
untethered by the memory of it.
哦 你会记住今天的
Oh you will remember this day.
直到倒下长眠 再也无法醒来
Until you lay to slumber, never to awaken.
我觉得 我们已经尽了最大努力
I fear we have let events run the best of us.
或许来杯小酒 可以让我们冷静下头脑
Perhaps a cup of wine to er, cool the head.
这里简直就是荒蛮之地
We are long past civilized recourse.
你丈夫一直紧迫逼人 我倒想看看如何收场
Your husband presses issue. I would see it closed.
我也一样
As would I.
这东西 能令结果有所不同?
Can I believe this will make a difference?
打开瞧瞧呗
Open it and see.
这恶心的东西是什么?
What is this abomination?
是Licinia躯体的
But a piece of the whole.
一部分
Licinia.
她是Crassus的表亲
Cousin of Crassus.
你杀了Licinia?
You murdered Licinia?
不 是你妻子杀的
No. Your wife did.
他撒谎
He lies.
杀人手段 残忍至极
A most heinous act.
我本来答应 要帮她隐瞒这事的
One I was content to help obscure,
她也答应 要帮我们求得你的资助
under promise of her aid in obtaining your favor.
现在 恐怕Licinia的尸体要重现天日了
Now I fear Licinia's body may resurface.
或者出现在贵宅大堂 如何?
On the grounds of your villa, perhaps?
我真想撕烂你的嘴!
I will see the tongue ripped from your fucking mouth!
哪怕我的嘴烂了 也照样能吐露真相
Even so ruined, it would yet speak the truth.
Cladius啊
Cladius.
你要相信我 这事不是我做的
You cannot believe me capable of such a thing.
我同意资助了
Patronage is granted.
我会留下一部分人
A portion of my men will remain stationed
保证以后不再发生此类尴尬事件
against further embarrassments.
其它的事 跟Ilithyia去谈吧
Make all other arrangements with Ilithyia.
她会继续留在卡普亚
She will be remaining here in Capua.
不!
No!
冒犯Batiatus家族的人
No man is above retribution
没人可以
for offenses committed
逃过惩罚
against the House of Batiatus.
不管你是角斗士
No gladiator.
还是战神
No Champion.
甚至是身边的守卫
Even the men that guard you,
有任何欺瞒或胜任不力 都一样会获罪
should they be guilty of deceit or incompetence.
Hector发现钥匙丢了
Hector found his key removed.
于是他的脑袋也跟着没了
His head follows.
错在我
The fault lies in my own breast,
野心太大
with heart grown too large.
完全没关注到这回事
This cannot stand.
Claudius Glaber副将
Legatus Claudius Glaber
现在是我们尊贵无比的资助人
is now our honored Patron.
他让我看到我的慷慨之错
And he has opened my eyes to the error of my generosity.
必须矫正
One that demands correction.
咬牙忍痛
Embrace the pain.
这是唯一能救你的法子
It is the only way.
我希望你和Crixus告一段落了
I expect your meetings with Crixus to end.
Quintus啊...
Quintus...
你给我闭嘴
Do not fucking speak.
你把我当傻瓜 还没侮辱够我么
That you would think me a fool is insult enough.
我一直都知情
I have always known.
不说是因为这样能让你开心
And turned eye away only because it made you happy,
所以我也从不多想
and caused me no thought.
这种日子结束了
Those days have ended.
把注意力转移到诞育孩子这事上吧
Set your attentions towards our child.
别让他们看笑话
And do not see them stray.
够了!
Enough!
Crixus啊!
Crixus!
让他们待一会儿
Grant them a moment.
他曾经是我们的战神
He was our Champion once.
他值得如许尊重
Allow him such respect.
我毁了我们的未来
I have destroyed us.
但我们还活着啊
We yet live.
他们要把你带去哪儿?
Where do they take you?
我不知道
I do not know.
我会争得自由的
I will win my freedom.
不找到你 我誓不罢休
I will not rest until I find you.
时间到了
It is time.
就像Barca一样 他也在说自由
He speaks of freedom, as did Barca.
我答应你 我会帮他争取自由
I give you my word, that I shall aid him in the seeking of it.
不 你必须制止他
No. You must not let him broach the subject.
Barca没有自由
Barca was not freed.
Batiatus杀了他
Batiatus took his life.
该死的 你们这些罗马混蛋
Fuck ass, you Roman cock.
闭上你的臭嘴
Shut your fucking mouth.
别跟他们硬碰硬
I would caution softer words.
这里越来越他妈恶心了
The shit keeps rising higher in this fucking hole.
或许当愤怒达到顶峰
Perhaps it best not to be present,
就自然会要发泄了
when it fills the mouth.
你这话什么意思?
What do you speak of?
没什么意思
I speak of nothing.
没意思听上去像是想逃跑
Nothing sounds much like escape.
那么 "没意思" 如何能避过Batiatus
And how would "Nothing" find way past Batiatus
和他那些阴魂不散的罗马侍卫?
and all his fucking Romans?
只有一条路
There is but one path.
我们杀出去
We kill them all.